<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Well, I should have written that down | Osher Azulay</title><link>https://osheraz.github.io/blog/</link><atom:link href="https://osheraz.github.io/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Well, I should have written that down</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 05 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://osheraz.github.io/media/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url><title>Well, I should have written that down</title><link>https://osheraz.github.io/blog/</link></image><item><title>Mapping, Perception and More</title><link>https://osheraz.github.io/blog/slam/</link><pubDate>Tue, 05 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://osheraz.github.io/blog/slam/</guid><description>&lt;p align="center">
&lt;img width="400" height="300" src="./test.png">
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;br />&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Well, i took a really nice course last semester, which was all about autonomous driving. I really liked it because it was a hands-on course, with some of the nicest projects. The course introduced some of the core functions of autonomous driving system, such as localization and mapping, spatial perception and route planning which later on focus on deep learning solutions.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Throughout the course, i thought it would be great to write a brief description about the projects i have done, for later projects i might do.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="project-1">Project #1&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>TODO: add the code here&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="topics">Topics&lt;/h4>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;input checked="" disabled="" type="checkbox"> Mapping and Localization&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;input checked="" disabled="" type="checkbox"> Probabilistic Occupancy Grid&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;input checked="" disabled="" type="checkbox"> Iterative Closet Points (ICP)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Modeling and understanding the environment is a crucial task for autonomous robotics, in particular for mobile robots. Occupancy Grid Mapping refers to a family of computer algorithms in probabilistic robotics for mobile robots. This address the problem of generating maps from noisy and uncertain sensor measurement data, with the assumption that the robot pose is known. The basic idea of the occupancy grid is to represent a map of the environment as an evenly spaced field of binary random variables each representing the presence of an obstacle at that location in the environment. In this project, we experienced with real captured driving data - &lt;code>KITTI Dataset&lt;/code>. The data-set contains 6 hours of traffic scenarios at 10–100 Hz using a variety of sensor modalities such as high-resolution color and grayscale stereo cameras, a Velodyne 3D laser scanner, and a high-precision GPS/IMU inertial navigation system.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Example &lt;strong>inline math&lt;/strong> &lt;code>$\nabla F(\mathbf{x}_{n})$&lt;/code> renders as $\nabla F(\mathbf{x}_{n})$.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The goal of an occupancy mapping algorithm is to estimate the posterior probability over maps given the data: $p(m\mid z_{1:t},x_{1:t}) $p(m\mid z_{{1:t}},x_{{1:t}})$
, where &lt;code>m&lt;/code> is the map, $z_{1:t}}z_{{1:t}}$ is the set of measurements from time 1 to t, and $x_{1:t}}x_{{1:t}$ is the set of robot poses from time 1 to t. The controls and odometry data play no part in the occupancy grid mapping algorithm since the path is assumed known.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>To implement the occupancy map, i used the &lt;code>pykitti&lt;/code> python package, which is a light package of minimal set of tools for working the the KITTI dataset. Basically, after passing the path of the recording, it provides each of the sensors data via generators for easy sequential access. This package assumes that you have already downloaded the calibration data associated with the sequences you want to work on, and that the directory structure is unchanged from the original structure laid out in the KITTI zip files.&lt;/p>
&lt;pre>&lt;code>def pykitti_dataset():
# Change this to the directory where you store KITTI data
curr_dir_path = os.getcwd()
basedir = curr_dir_path + '/kitti_data'
# Specify the dataset to load
date = '2011_09_26'
drive = '0013'
# Load the data.
dataset = pykitti.raw(basedir, date, drive)
return dataset
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;p>which lets your access the following:&lt;/p>
&lt;pre>&lt;code># dataset.calib: Calibration data are accessible as a named tuple
# dataset.timestamps: Timestamps are parsed into a list of datetime objects
# dataset.oxts: List of OXTS packets and 6-dof poses as named tuples
# dataset.camN: Returns a generator that loads individual images from camera N
# dataset.get_camN(idx): Returns the image from camera N at idx
# dataset.gray: Returns a generator that loads monochrome stereo pairs (cam0, cam1)
# dataset.get_gray(idx): Returns the monochrome stereo pair at idx
# dataset.rgb: Returns a generator that loads RGB stereo pairs (cam2, cam3)
# dataset.get_rgb(idx): Returns the RGB stereo pair at idx
# dataset.velo: Returns a generator that loads velodyne scans as [x,y,z,reflectance]
# dataset.get_velo(idx): Returns the velodyne scan at idx
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre></description></item></channel></rss>